Register of the Evgeniia Sergeevna Isaenko Papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Evgeniia Sergeevna Isaenko papers
1902-1971
2000C67
Hoover Institution Archives
1 manuscript box, 10 microfilm reels (1.9 linear feet)
Writings, correspondence, printed matter, and photographs, relating to Russian literature and to Russian émigré affairs. Includes some papers of Aleksei Leonidovich Isaenko, husband of Evgeniia Isaenko.
Isaenko, Evgeniia Sergeevna
Access
Collection is open for research. Boxes 12-15 not microfilmed, originals at the Museum of Russian Culture, San Francisco.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired.
Location of Originals
In part, originals in: Museum of Russian Culture, San Francisco.
Biography
E. S. Isaenko was born Evgeniia Pechatkina in Askhabad on 16 December 1899, the daughter of General Sergei Pechatkin. Living in Harbin following the Revolution, she was among the first Russian students to depart for the United States in the early 1920s, where she continued her education at Pomona College. For personal reasons, she left college and went to San Francisco, making her living performing menial labor as a packer in a factory, dishwasher, seamstress, etc. Meanwhile, she devoted her free time to Russian social life, actively participating in musical, theatrical and literary presentations. She directed and acted in plays, and wrote articles, reviews, short stories and two books, Perekati-Pole (published in 1953) and Petr Ivanovich (1961).
Though she married Aleksei Leonidovich Isaenko and assumed his last name, she continued to publish under her maiden name. Her husband was also active in the San Francisco Russian community as librarian of the Russian Club and Russian Center. He was born in Orenburg in 1894, the son of Major General Leonid Isaenko. Receiving a degree in law from Moscow University in 1917, he joined the White Army in Siberia during the Civil War. He arrived in America in 1923, and met Evgeniia Sergeevna through their common interest in theatrical and social activities. He died in 1957; Evgeniia Sergeevna Isaenko died in Burlingame, California, in July 1969.
Evgeniia Sergeevna Isaenko
? Born, Ashkhabad, Zakaspiiskaia oblast', Russia
1922 Studied at Vladivostok University
1924 Studied at Pomona College, Claremont, California
1953 Author, Perekati-Pole
1961 Author, Petr Ivanovich
1970? Died, San Francisco, California
Aleksei Leonidovich Isaenko
1894 July 2 (N.S.) Born, Orenburg, Russia
1917 Law degree, Moscow University Graduated, Aleksandrovskoe voennoe uchilishche
1918-1920 Officer, Orenburg Cossack Host
1923 Arrived in the United States
1957 November 15 Died, San Francisco, California
Scope and Content Note
This collection contains the papers of Evgeniia Sergeevna Isaenko, an émigré writer and poet, author of the novel Perekati-Pole, published, as were many of her works, under her maiden name Evgeniia Pechatkina (she appears also to have published under the initials E. P., as well as under the pseudonyms E. Sergeeva and Maksim Davydov). Isaenko was an active figure in the Russian émigré community, staging plays and taking part in other social events, particularly those related to the Russian Center.
The collection also contains biographical materials relating to and correspondence of her husband, Aleksei Leonidovich Isaenko, a former army officer and director of the Russian Center library.
Detailed processing and preservation microfilming of these materials were made possible by a generous grant from the National Endowment for the Humanities and by matching funds from the Hoover Institution and the Museum of Russian Culture. The grant also provides depositing a microfilm copy in the Hoover Institution Archives. The original materials remain at the Museum of Russian Culture, San Francisco, as its property. A transfer table of corresponding box and reel numbers is available at the Hoover Institution Archives.
The Hoover Institution assumes all responsibility for notifying users that they must comply with the copyright law of the United States (Title 17 United States Code) and Hoover Rules for the Use and Reproduction of Archival Materials.
Isaenko, Aleksei Leonidovich, 1894-1957.; Russia.; Russian literature.; Russians--United States.; United States.
- Biographical File, 1902-1971 (Box 1-2)
  Scope and Contents note
  Autobiographical note, clipping, identity papers, scrapbooks and other materials arranged alphabetically by physical form. Includes biographical materials of family members
  - Addresses (lists and business cards) (Folder 1: 1)
  - Autobiographical note (Folder 1: 2)
  - Clipping (Folder 1: 3)
  - Journalistic accreditation (Folder 1: 4)
  - Programs (Folder 1: 5)
  - Scrapbooks (Folder 1: 6-8)
  - Scrapbooks (Box-folder 2: 1)
  - Subject file - Family
    - Isaenko, Aleksei Leonidovich (husband)
      - Birth certificate (Folder 2: 2)
      - Correspondence with first wife, Mariia Isaenko (Folder 2: 3)
      - Immigration papers. (Folder 2: 4)
        Includes photograph, 1923, and certificate of naturalization, 1929
      - Military service records (Folder 2: 5)
      - Obituaries. (Folder 2: 6)
        Includes death notices and related materials. Also includes letter from N. Lapenson to N. A. Slobodchikov, 1971, forwarding these materials
      - Passport (Folder 2: 7)
      - Residence permit (Folder 2: 8)
      - School records (Folder 2: 9)
      - Writings. (Folder 2: 10)
        Notes and poetry
    - Isaenko, Leonid Fedorovich (father-in-law). (Folder 2: 11)
      Military service records
    - Pechatkin, Sergei Evgen'evich (father). (Folder 2: 12)
      Sympathy cards and letters on death of, 1947
  - Miscellany (Folder 2: 13)
- Correspondence, 1928-1968 (Box 2-3)
  Includes correspondence of A. L. Isaenko. Arranged alphabetically by name of correspondent
  - General, 1934-1962 and undated (Folder 2: 14)
  - Unidentified, 1945-1968 and undated (Folder 2: 15)
  - Al'tman, A., 1945 (Folder 2: 16)
  - Antonii, Archbishop of Los Angeles, 1967 (Folder 2: 17)
  - Baillet, Margarete, 1953 (Folder 2: 18)
  - Berezov, R., 1954 (Folder 2: 19)
  - Borzov, Nikolai V., 1935-1953 (Folder 2: 20)
  - Briditskii (Bryditzki), Victor F., 1946 (Folder 2: 21)
    Includes writing entitled "Tishina," [1946]. Holograph
  - Buk, Zoia Andreevna, 1949-1950 (Folder 2: 22)
  - Bushkov, Mr., 1949 (Folder 2: 23)
  - Bykova, babushka, 1949 and undated (Folder 2: 24)
  - Chekhov, Mikhail, 1944 (Folder 2: 25)
  - Colman, S., n.d. (Folder 2: 26)
  - Consolidated Committee of the Russian National Organizations, 1934-1951 (Folder 2: 27)
  - Demidov, V., Rev., 1949-1950 (Folder 2: 28)
  - Destina, Vera, 1945 (Folder 2: 29)
    Includes related third-party correspondence to and from B. K. Grachev and N. N. Gracheva, c. 1934
  - El'nitskii, Ivan and Nataliia, 1968 (Folder 2: 30)
  - Emel'ianova, Ol'ga Nikolaevna, n.d. (Folder 3: 1)
  - Evreinov, Nikolai Nikolaevich, 1950-1951 (Folder 3: 2)
  - Flanin (?), F., 1942 (Folder 3: 3)
  - Foster, Liudmila A., 1968 (Folder 3: 4)
  - Gerasimenko, A., [1942]-1943 (Folder 3: 5)
  - Glagolin, B., n.d. (Folder 3: 6)
  - Glebov, Ivan A. (Gleboff, John A.), 1954-1958 (Folder 3: 7)
  - Gornyi, Sergei, n.d. (Folder 3: 8)
    Includes photograph
  - Grebenshchikov, Georgii D., 1941-1954 (Folder 3: 9)
  - Gribanovskii, Pavel (Gribanovsky, Paul), 1953 (Folder 3: 10)
  - Grot, E., n.d. (Folder 3: 11)
  - Guins, George C., 1942-1954 (Folder 3: 12)
    Includes third-party correspondence to Guins
  - Iastrebov, Innokentii, 1949 (Folder 3: 13)
  - Isaenko, A. L., 1928-1929 and undated (Folder 3: 14)
  - Iur'eva, Militsa, 1943 (Folder 3: 15)
  - Izdebskaia, Galina, 1943-1946 (Folder 3: 16)
    Includes clippings and letter from Witold Izdebsky
  - Kasperuk, Konstantin, 1948-1951 and undated (Folder 3: 17)
  - Kazem-Bek, A., 1942 (Folder 3: 18)
  - Khorvat, Kamilla, 1949-1950 (Folder 3: 19)
  - Kirchev, N. S. and Kircheva, P. M., 1943-1945 (Folder 3: 20)
  - Konstantinov, Petr Filaretovich, 1945-1949 (Folder 3: 21)
  - Korovai-Metelitskii, Aleksei Longinovich, 1964-1969 (Folder 3: 22)
    Includes poetry
  - Kovalenko, Georgii, Rev., 1950 (Folder 3: 23)
  - Lapenson, Nadezhda, 1950-1954 (Folder 3: 24)
  - Lavreniuk (Lawreniuk), S. V., 1953-1954 (Folder 3: 25)
  - Loukashkin, Anatolii Stepanovich, 1966 (Folder 3: 26)
  - MacGuire (von Arnol'd), Antonina, 1949-1950 and undated (Folder 3: 27)
  - Mairovskii, Georgii Dmitrievich, 1950 (Folder 3: 28)
  - Mazurova, A., 1945-1951 (Folder 3: 29)
  - Mort, V., 1959-1960 (Folder 3: 30)
  - Narokov, N., 1954-1958 (Folder 3: 31)
  - Nasonova, Anna Petrovna, 1951-1954 (Folder 3: 32)
  - Nekrasov, Boris, 1950 and undated (Folder 3: 33)
  - Osip'ian, Aramais, 1954 (Folder 3: 34)
  - Pechatkin, Sergei Evgen'evich, 1928-1930 (Folder 3: 35)
  - Pirang, Aleksei Nikolaevich, 1949-1953 (Folder 3: 36)
  - Pirang, Andrei Nikolaevich, 1946-1950 (Folder 3: 37)
    Includes Pirang's immigration papers
  - Podberesky, N., n.d. (Folder 3: 38)
  - Polon, A., 1950 and undated (Folder 3: 39)
  - Porokhovshchikov, Petr S. (Porohovshikov, Peter S.), 1945 (Folder 3: 40)
  - Redin, Kira, 1967 (Folder 3: 41)
  - Roshchina, E., 1951 (Folder 3: 42)
  - Rozen, E. K., 1951-1954 and undated (Folder 3: 43)
  - Russkaia zhizn' ( Russian Life), 1942-1953 (Folder 3: 44)
    Includes third-party correspondence to editor
  - Sabov, G., 1943-1953 (Folder 3: 45)
  - San Francisco Committee for the Aid of Russian Disabled Veterans Outside of Russia, Inc., 1958-1963 (Folder 3: 46)
  - Satovskii, Iu., 1940 (Folder 3: 47)
  - Seryshev, Innokentii Nikolaevich, 1953-1961 (Folder 3: 48)
  - Sheremet'eva, E., 1959 (Folder 3: 49)
  - Shrubak (Schrubak), M. A., 1950 (Folder 3: 50)
  - Shul'gin, P. (Folder 3: 51)
  - Sudakov, Aleksandr (Sudakoff, Alexander), 1942-1945 (Folder 3: 52)
  - Svoboda, Pavel, 1954 (Folder 3: 53)
  - Turkova (Tourkoff), M., 1958 (Folder 3: 54)
  - Ungern, Iurii, 1948 and undated (Folder 3: 55)
  - Valiansky, Vitalii A., 1954 (Folder 3: 56)
  - Varypaeva, V., 1942 (Folder 3: 57)
  - Vatel', N., 1951-1953 (Folder 3: 58)
  - Volkov, Boris Nikolaevich, 1950 (Folder 3: 59)
    Copies of letters to the editor of Russkaia zhizn'
  - Voloshin, Alex, 1953 (Folder 3: 60)
  - Vol'skii, Andrei and Vera, 1950 (Folder 3: 61)
  - von Mohrenschildt, Dimitri, n.d. (Folder 3: 62)
  - Zabelin, P., 1949-1950 (Folder 3: 63)
  - Zhitkova, D., 1956 (Folder 3: 64)
- Speeches and Writings, 1929-1969 and undated (Box 4-8)
  Short stories, novellas, poetry, newspaper articles, arranged chronologically by title
  - General
    - Addresses in honor of various individuals (Folder 4: 1)
    - Notebooks, n.d. (Folder 4: 2-6)
      Include inserts. Mainly holograph drafts of works, but also include entries of a diary nature
    - Notebooks (Box-folder 5: 1-3)
    - Notes, n.d. (Folder 5: 4)
    - Poetry, n.d. (Folder 5: 5)
    - Reviews of plays, lectures, literary-musical evenings and similar events (Folder 5: 6)
  - "A. K. Tolstoi,", n.d. (Box-folder 6: 1)
    Typescript
  - "Chaikovskii,", n.d. (Folder 6: 2)
    Holograph and typescript
  - "Den' russkago rebenka,", n.d. (Folder 6: 3)
  - "Dragotsennaia devochka,", n.d. (Folder 6: 4)
  - "Eia pamiati.. Ekaterina Mironovna Chepigo,", n.d. (Folder 6: 5)
  - "El'f,", n.d. (Folder 6: 6)
  - "Gogolevskii iubileinyi spektakl'", n.d. (Folder 6: 7)
  - "Iavliautsia li Mertvyia dushi Gogolia anafemoi ili apofeozom Rossii?", n.d. (Folder 6: 8)
  - "Inostrannoe vliianie na russkuiu kul'turu,", n.d. (Folder 6: 9)
  - "Irina Blank,", n.d. (Folder 6: 10)
  - "Izmena,", n.d. (Folder 6: 11)
  - "Izobretatel',", n.d. (Folder 6: 12)
  - "Kak ia ukral arkhiereiskikh pievchykh,", n.d. (Folder 6: 13)
  - "Kontora,", n.d. (Folder 6: 14)
  - "Krestiny,", n.d. (Folder 6: 15)
  - "Lana,", n.d. (Folder 6: 16)
  - "Led'ka,", n.d. (Folder 6: 17)
  - "Malen'kii brodiaga,", n.d. (Folder 6: 18)
  - "Maskaradnyi eskiz,", n.d. (Folder 6: 19)
    Holograph
  - "Mest',", n.d. (Folder 6: 20)
  - "Motyl'ki,", n.d. (Folder 6: 21)
  - "My Boy Friend," (Folder 6: 22)
  - "Nashi 'zasedateli',", n.d. (Folder 6: 23)
  - "Nasmork,", n.d. (Folder 6: 24)
  - "Nechistaia sila,", n.d. (Folder 6: 25)
  - "Nian'ka i promyvanie,", n.d. (Folder 6: 26)
  - "Nochnye krasavitsy,", n.d. (Folder 6: 27)
  - "Ob"edinenie talantov,", n.d. (Folder 6: 28)
  - "Obrashchenie,", n.d. (Folder 6: 29)
  - "Odin den' v atel'e," (Folder 6: 30)
  - "Ona i ia,", n.d. (Folder 6: 31)
  - "Opravdanie 'Oblomovshchiny',", n.d. (Folder 6: 32)
  - "Oproverzhenie,", n.d. (Folder 6: 33)
  - "Opyty,", n.d. (Folder 6: 34)
  - "Otets Il'ia,", n.d. (Folder 6: 35)
  - "Otviet na zashchitu 'Priznanie Patriarkha' B. S. Glagolina,", n.d. (Folder 6: 36)
  - "Pamiati stareishago chlena organizatsii 'ART' G. A. Kalinina,", n.d. (Folder 6: 37)
  - "Panikhida,", n.d. (Folder 6: 38)
    Typescript. Includes clipping
  - "Paskhal'nyi nabrosok,", n.d. (Folder 6: 39)
  - "Piatoe izmerenie,", n.d. (Folder 6: 40)
  - "Pod novyi god,", n.d. (Folder 6: 41)
  - "Predskazanie,", n.d. (Folder 6: 42)
  - "Proidennyi put',", n.d. (Folder 6: 43)
  - "Putevye zametki,", n.d. (Folder 6: 44)
  - Review of Boris Gerasimov-Sherwood, Dva tigra, n.d. (Folder 6: 45)
  - Review of Irina Saburova, Posle, n.d. (Folder 6: 46)
  - Review of Nikolai Ul'ianov, Atossa, n.d. (Folder 6: 47)
  - Review of Victor Petrov, Saga Fort Ross, n.d. (Folder 6: 48)
  - Reviews of various issues of the periodical Sovremennik, n.d. (Folder 6: 49)
  - "Rozhdenie Russkoi zhizni,", n.d. (Folder 6: 50)
  - "Rozhdestvenskii arbuz,", n.d. (Folder 6: 51)
  - "Rukovodstvo k ukroshcheniiu muzhchiny,", n.d. (Box-folder 7: 1)
  - "Russkaia zhenshchina v muzyke i literature,", n.d. (Folder 7: 2)
  - "Russkie liudi,", n.d. (Folder 7: 3)
  - "Russkie v Kalifornii,", n.d. (Folder 7: 4)
  - "Russkiia dieti v biedie,", n.d. (Folder 7: 5)
  - "Shestero,", n.d. (Folder 7: 6)
  - "Sila tantsa,", n.d. (Folder 7: 7)
  - "Simvolika Vishnevogo sada,", n.d. (Folder 7: 8)
  - Speech in honor of unidentified individual (Folder 7: 9)
  - "Sumerki,", n.d. (Folder 7: 10)
  - "Sviataia lozh',", n.d. (Folder 7: 11)
  - "Sviataia zemlia,", n.d. (Folder 7: 12)
  - "Teatr v San-Frantsisko,", n.d. (Folder 7: 13)
  - Untitled article honoring Russkaia zhizn' on the occasion of its 15 th year of publication, n.d. (Folder 7: 14)
  - "V gostiakh u Litfonda," (Folder 7: 15)
  - "V letnei kabine,", n.d. (Folder 7: 16)
  - "Varen'e,", n.d. (Folder 7: 17)
  - "Veshchee,", n.d. (Folder 7: 18)
  - "Veter neset tuchu,", n.d. (Folder 7: 19)
  - "Vozvrashchenie,", n.d. (Folder 7: 20)
  - "Za bortom,", n.d. (Folder 7: 21)
  - "Za chashkoi chaiu,", n.d. (Folder 7: 22)
  - "Russkaia zhenshchina v emigratsii,"., 1929 (Folder 7: 23)
  - "Apchkhi," Nashe vremia, 1935 (Folder 7: 24)
    Printed copy
  - "Vanda," Rampa, 1941 (Folder 7: 25)
    Typescript and printed copy. Includes entire issue #1 of Rampa, edited by Isaenko
  - "Studencheskaia odisseia,"., 1946 (Folder 7: 26)
  - Speech at a banquet in honor of S. A. Zharov, 1946 November 3 (Folder 7: 27)
  - Perekati-pole, 1953
    - Correspondence, 1947-1960 (Folder 7: 28)
    - Financial statements. (Folder 7: 29)
      Includes receipts and ledger. May also include financial records for sales of Petr Ivanovich
    - Reviews (Folder 7: 30)
    - Miscellany. (Folder 7: 31)
      Includes blurb and other prepublication materials, lists of booksellers, and advertisements
  - "Park Montalvo,"., 1955 June 8 (Folder 7: 32)
  - "Pechat' sud'by,"., 1956 February 23 (Folder 7: 33)
  - Petr Ivanovich, 1961 (Box 8)
    General note
    See also Perekati-pole/Financial statements
    - Correspondence, 1960-1969 (Folder 8: 1)
    - Reviews (Folder 8: 2)
  - "Ioann Damaskin,"., 1968 September 16 (Folder 8: 3)
  - "Svet i teni,"., 1969 (Folder 8: 4)
- Plays, n.d. (Box 8-10)
  Plays and sketches by V. Mort, N. Narokov, A. Zhernakova, and others, staged by Isaenko or with her participation. May contain plays written by Isaenko. Arranged alphabetically by name of author
  - General and unidentified. (Folder 8: 5-7)
    Includes fragments, sketches adapted from other works, monologues, individual roles, notes for actors
  - A-I (Box-folder 9: 1)
  - K-N (Folder 9: 2)
  - R (Folder 9: 3)
  - S (Folder 9: 4)
  - T (Box-folder 10: 1)
  - U-Z (Box-folder 10: 2)
- Subject File, 1932-1968 (Box 10-11)
  Clippings, correspondence, writings, posters, scrapbook and other matter, arranged alphabetically by heading
  - ART Society (Folder 10: 3)
  - Nikolaev, Konstantin Nikolaevich (Folder 10: 4)
  - Ostrenko, A. (Folder 10: 5)
  - Radio Liberty. (Folder 10: 6)
    Materials relating to a literary-musical fundraiser for the benefit of Radio Liberty, San Francisco, 1968
  - Refugees (Folder 10: 7)
  - Russian Center (Russkii tsentr), San Francisco (Folder 10: 8)
  - Russkaia Pravoslavnaia Tserkov' (Folder 10: 9)
  - Shipunov, Ivan (Folder 10: 10)
  - Tolstoy Foundation (Folder 10: 11)
  - Miscellany (Box-folder 11: 1-3)
- Photographs, 1920s-1960s (Box 12-15)
  Albums, loose prints and negatives, arranged by subject
  - Negatives (Folder 12: 1)
  - Prints
    - 34 prints of E. S. and A. L. Isaenko, together, separately, and in groups (Folder 12: 2)
    - 5 prints of the Russian Club, San Francisco, 1925 (Folder 12: 3)
    - 120 prints of unidentified and miscellaneous individuals, groups, events, and places (Folder 12: 4)
  - Albums. (Box-folder 13: 1-2)
    Primarily family and vacation photographs. Include depictions of flood in Harbin, China, 1920s
  - Albums (Box-folder 14: 1-4)
  - Albums (Box-folder 15: 1-3)
  - One oversize photograph of unidentified actor in makeup (Folder 15: 4)
- Incremental Materials (Box 1)
  Materials acquired after the microfilming of the Museum of Russian Culture, San Francisco collection